<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pranmod01.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pranmod01.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-13T00:03:22+00:00</updated><id>https://pranmod01.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">What the Wild Taught Us - Reflections from My Trip to Africa</title><link href="https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/africa-trip/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What the Wild Taught Us - Reflections from My Trip to Africa"/><published>2025-08-12T15:29:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-12T15:29:16+00:00</updated><id>https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/africa-trip</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/africa-trip/"><![CDATA[<p>This summer, my parents and I traveled to Kenya and Tanzania, visiting Maasai Mara, Serengeti, and the Ngorongoro Crater. The safari was more than just a vacation — it gave us a chance to step back and think about the world and our place in it. We expected to see animals in their natural habitat, but what we gained was a deeper perspective.</p> <h1 id="a-role-reversal">A Role Reversal</h1> <p>On our game drives, we noticed something interesting. Seated in our vehicle, essentially a cage on wheels, we realized we were the ones confined, observing animals roam free in their world. It was a complete reversal of the typical zoo experience, where animals are enclosed and humans look on from the outside.</p> <p>There was something powerful about seeing wildlife on its own terms: lions napping in the shade, elephants gathering in family groups, birds moving in unison across a vast sky. These creatures weren’t just surviving, they were thriving because they were in the space they were meant to inhabit.</p> <p>But alongside the awe was a deep sadness. This space, their space, is shrinking. Not long ago, animals like these roamed freely across much larger territories. Now, seeing them live fully requires hours of travel into remote protected areas. The contrast is sobering. It reminds us just how much we’ve taken, and how little remains untouched.</p> <h1 id="personal-reflections">Personal Reflections</h1> <p>What made this journey even more meaningful was how differently each of us absorbed it, how personal our takeaways were, shaped by our own lives and values.</p> <p><strong>My mom</strong> was struck by the extraordinary hospitality of the people we met. There was a sense of pride in how they served, treating each guest not as a transaction but as someone truly welcome, like a friend stepping into their home. <em>Her reflection</em>: When we welcome others into our own home, we should do it with that same spirit: thoughtful, warm, and generous.</p> <p><strong>I</strong> was inspired by our safari guide. His knowledge was encyclopedic: he could spot animals in the distance, explain their behaviors and habitats, and photograph them beautifully. Yet what stood out most was his humility. Even during breaks, he was reading, learning, deepening his craft. <em>My reflection</em>: Obsession with your craft, paired with humility and curiosity, goes further than short-term motivation ever could.</p> <p><strong>My dad</strong> saw in the wild a mirror of human society. Nature was, at times, ruthless, a constant fight for food, dominance, and survival. But it was also full of care: elephant herds protecting their young, lions grooming each other, birds taking turns watching for predators. <em>His reflection</em>: The natural world reflects us. It can be cutthroat like the corporate world, but also familial and community-oriented like a healthy society. The circle of life connects us more closely than we often realize.</p> <h1 id="a-shared-lesson">A Shared Lesson</h1> <p>Though our takeaways varied, it was evident that each reflection was shaped by where we are in life. The same experience offered different insights to each of us, and that’s the beauty of travel done with awareness. When you’re open, the world has a way of speaking to you personally.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This summer, my parents and I traveled to Kenya and Tanzania, visiting Maasai Mara, Serengeti, and the Ngorongoro Crater. The safari was more than just a vacation — it gave us a chance to step back and think about the world and our place in it. We expected to see animals in their natural habitat, but what we gained was a deeper perspective.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Neuromatch NeuroAI Reflections</title><link href="https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/nm-nai-reflections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neuromatch NeuroAI Reflections"/><published>2025-07-26T09:12:49+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-26T09:12:49+00:00</updated><id>https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/nm-nai-reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/nm-nai-reflections/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="neuroai"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry></feed>