<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pranmod01.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pranmod01.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-19T17:07:02+00:00</updated><id>https://pranmod01.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Geography of Belonging - Reflections on 34 Countries and Counting</title><link href="https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/travel-thesis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Geography of Belonging - Reflections on 34 Countries and Counting"/><published>2025-08-15T22:09:02+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-15T22:09:02+00:00</updated><id>https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/travel-thesis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/travel-thesis/"><![CDATA[<p>As I conclude my travels through my 34th country, I find myself reflecting not just on the places I have visited, but on why I have always been drawn to travel.</p> <p>Growing up, my family did not travel much internationally. But even as a child, I dreamed of seeing the world. That dream began to take shape in college, when a friend introduced me to the possibilities of budget travel: finding $200 flights to faraway capitals, piecing together layovers into makeshift itineraries, staying in hostels where a bunk bed came with ten strangers and a dozen travel stories.</p> <p>Since starting my full-time job, I have visited 24 countries in just two years. I am constantly aware that the ability to move so freely across borders is not a given. That awareness changes how I travel: I tip more generously, I ask more questions, I try to notice the invisible work that makes my movement possible. Sometimes it also carries a quiet guilt, knowing I can leave while others cannot.</p> <p>I have traveled solo, with friends, and with family, and each experience has taught me something different. What has stayed constant is the way travel heightens my attention. I find myself drawn to overheard conversations in unfamiliar languages, compelled to follow the sound of music around a corner, always reaching toward something just beyond my understanding.</p> <p>Perhaps this attention began long before I ever boarded a plane. I spent nearly equal parts of my childhood in India and the United States, and people often asked me which culture I preferred or felt more connected to. Those questions trained me, from a young age, to notice how people think, act, and believe differently. Observing cultural contrasts became part of my daily life, whether I wanted it to or not. In some ways, my travels now feel like a continuation of that early habit, only on a much wider stage.</p> <p>I think of my travels as a form of informal cultural anthropology: observing how and why people live the way they do, and how their traditions came to be. In Tanzania, I learned about local marriage customs—family negotiations, ceremonial exchanges, multi-day celebrations—that mirrored what I had grown up seeing in India. Two cultures, separated by continents and histories, had found strikingly similar ways of marking life’s milestones. I wondered if the similarity came from shared values around kinship, or if marriage rituals everywhere simply bend toward the same human needs: connection, community, continuity.</p> <p>Beyond these deeper questions, I am drawn to culture’s most vivid expressions: food, music, and language. These already shape my personal life, so encountering them in new forms feels like a continuation of something I have always been doing. I remember walking through the spice markets of Doha, where vendors called out prices in Arabic while the scent of cardamom and saffron hung heavy in the desert air. Or standing in a small church in Slovakia, listening to a choir practice traditional hymns that seemed to echo off centuries-old stone walls. These moments are my favorite kind of research—felt before they are understood.</p> <p>Travel also brings moments of discomfort. I have felt the heat rise in my face when I have butchered a local greeting, or the awkwardness of being served in a place where wages are low and tourism is high. And yet, I have also been surprised—like when I got hopelessly lost in the narrow streets of Yogyakarta in Indonesia, and a woman selling fruit from a roadside cart not only gave me directions but insisted on walking me halfway there, switching effortlessly between Indonesian and broken English to make sure I understood. These moments remind me that hospitality is often less about formality and more about small acts of care.</p> <p>In recent years, I have noticed how globalization reshapes the cultures I encounter. McDonald’s golden arches casting shadows over ancient temples in Singapore. Young people in rural Costa Rica scrolling through the same TikTok videos as teenagers in New York. In some places, this blending feels seamless; in others, it feels like erosion. I find myself asking: what is worth preserving, and what is worth letting go? Not all traditions should be preserved—many have roots in exclusion, patriarchy, or other systems of inequality. Yet with every tradition that disappears, something irreplaceable also fades.</p> <p>This tension is not something I witness only abroad. It lives in me. My upbringing braided together values from two different worlds, and sometimes they pull in opposite directions. I do not yet know which ones I will pass on and which I will release. Travel does not answer these questions, but it keeps me willing to sit with them.</p> <p>I expect my style of travel will shift over time. Perhaps I will move past the impulse to see everything and instead choose to stay longer: watch the same street at different hours, follow the arc of a conversation with someone I have met more than once.</p> <p>Seeing the world has never been just about the passport stamps. It’s about noticing the small threads that connect us: shared rituals, familiar laughter, the way a song or scent can feel like home halfway across the globe, while also honoring the differences that make each place irreplaceable. Travel sharpens my awareness of the cultures I carry within me, the ones I inherit, and the ones I choose moving forward. And perhaps the real journey is learning how to weave them together into a life that feels both rooted and open, a bridge between where I come from and everywhere I’ve yet to go.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As I conclude my travels through my 34th country, I find myself reflecting not just on the places I have visited, but on why I have always been drawn to travel.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What the Wild Taught Us - Reflections from My Trip to Africa</title><link href="https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/africa-trip/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What the Wild Taught Us - Reflections from My Trip to Africa"/><published>2025-08-12T15:29:16+00:00</published><updated>2025-08-12T15:29:16+00:00</updated><id>https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/africa-trip</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/africa-trip/"><![CDATA[<p>This summer, my parents and I traveled to Kenya and Tanzania, visiting Maasai Mara, Serengeti, and the Ngorongoro Crater. The safari was more than just a vacation — it gave us a chance to step back and think about the world and our place in it. We expected to see animals in their natural habitat, but what we gained was a deeper perspective.</p> <h1 id="a-role-reversal">A Role Reversal</h1> <p>On our game drives, we noticed something interesting. Seated in our vehicle, essentially a cage on wheels, we realized we were the ones confined, observing animals roam free in their world. It was a complete reversal of the typical zoo experience, where animals are enclosed and humans look on from the outside.</p> <p>There was something powerful about seeing wildlife on its own terms: lions napping in the shade, elephants gathering in family groups, birds moving in unison across a vast sky. These creatures weren’t just surviving, they were thriving because they were in the space they were meant to inhabit.</p> <p>But alongside the awe was a deep sadness. This space, their space, is shrinking. Not long ago, animals like these roamed freely across much larger territories. Now, seeing them live fully requires hours of travel into remote protected areas. The contrast is sobering. It reminds us just how much we’ve taken, and how little remains untouched.</p> <h1 id="personal-reflections">Personal Reflections</h1> <p>What made this journey even more meaningful was how differently each of us absorbed it, how personal our takeaways were, shaped by our own lives and values.</p> <p><strong>My mom</strong> was struck by the extraordinary hospitality of the people we met. There was a sense of pride in how they served, treating each guest not as a transaction but as someone truly welcome, like a friend stepping into their home. <em>Her reflection</em>: When we welcome others into our own home, we should do it with that same spirit: thoughtful, warm, and generous.</p> <p><strong>I</strong> was inspired by our safari guide. His knowledge was encyclopedic: he could spot animals in the distance, explain their behaviors and habitats, and photograph them beautifully. Yet what stood out most was his humility. Even during breaks, he was reading, learning, deepening his craft. <em>My reflection</em>: Obsession with your craft, paired with humility and curiosity, goes further than short-term motivation ever could.</p> <p><strong>My dad</strong> saw in the wild a mirror of human society. Nature was, at times, ruthless, a constant fight for food, dominance, and survival. But it was also full of care: elephant herds protecting their young, lions grooming each other, birds taking turns watching for predators. <em>His reflection</em>: The natural world reflects us. It can be cutthroat like the corporate world, but also familial and community-oriented like a healthy society. The circle of life connects us more closely than we often realize.</p> <h1 id="a-shared-lesson">A Shared Lesson</h1> <p>Though our takeaways varied, it was evident that each reflection was shaped by where we are in life. The same experience offered different insights to each of us, and that’s the beauty of travel done with awareness. When you’re open, the world has a way of speaking to you personally.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="travel"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This summer, my parents and I traveled to Kenya and Tanzania, visiting Maasai Mara, Serengeti, and the Ngorongoro Crater. The safari was more than just a vacation — it gave us a chance to step back and think about the world and our place in it. We expected to see animals in their natural habitat, but what we gained was a deeper perspective.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Neuromatch NeuroAI Reflections</title><link href="https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/nm-nai-reflections/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Neuromatch NeuroAI Reflections"/><published>2025-07-26T09:12:49+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-26T09:12:49+00:00</updated><id>https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/nm-nai-reflections</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pranmod01.github.io/blog/2025/nm-nai-reflections/"><![CDATA[<p>This summer, I completed the NeuroAI course offered by Neuromatch Academy, a volunteer-led organization providing research education and training at the intersection of neuroscience and machine learning. The course introduced key topics in biologically inspired AI, including neural coding, learning dynamics, and open problems in cognition, while emphasizing hands-on coding, peer collaboration, and engagement with current research. As someone who had been passively interested in NeuroAI, this course was foundational in helping me move from curiosity to genuine direction. It gave me the conceptual framework, technical skills, and intellectual community to explore the field seriously.</p> <p>I was especially drawn to tutorials like <strong>Macrolearning</strong> and <strong>Mysteries</strong>, which encouraged thinking beyond standard ML benchmarks. The Macrolearning module focused on how biological systems acquire and generalize knowledge over long timescales—from concept formation to learning to learn. I found it compelling because it addressed phenomena that current AI struggles with, such as continual learning and transfer across tasks, while offering frameworks for how these abilities might emerge from hierarchical and distributed representations. The Mysteries module took a different angle, introducing unsolved questions at the core of both AI and neuroscience—such as the nature of consciousness, how the brain balances generalization with specificity, and whether predictive coding frameworks can explain cognition. I appreciated its speculative nature and the invitation to engage with ambiguity and open-ended inquiry.</p> <p>As part of the course, my group completed a project comparing spiking neural networks (SNNs), recurrent neural networks (RNNs), and convolutional neural networks (CNNs) on visual working memory tasks. We examined how each model encoded, maintained, and retrieved visual information, and how performance degraded under noisy conditions. Using tools such as Representational Similarity Analysis (RSA), Dynamic Similarity Analysis (DSA), and fixed-point analysis, we investigated the robustness and representational dynamics of these architectures. The project deepened my interest in how neural geometry and temporal coding support cognition and how these insights could inform better AI design.</p> <p>What draws me to NeuroAI isn’t just the technical novelty—it’s the potential to build more responsible, interpretable AI systems by grounding them in the principles of biological intelligence. I’m particularly interested in how internal representations, goal structures, and dynamics in models shape behavior, topics increasingly relevant to efforts in interpretability and AI safety. Understanding how the brain handles ambiguity, motivation, and generalization could be key to creating AI systems that behave more reliably and in alignment with human values. I believe that NeuroAI offers not only scientific insight but also a principled foundation for ethical and robust AI development.</p> <p>This fall, I’ll be starting my MS in Computer Science at Columbia University, where I hope to explore these topics further!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="neuroai"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This summer, I completed the NeuroAI course offered by Neuromatch Academy, a volunteer-led organization providing research education and training at the intersection of neuroscience and machine learning. The course introduced key topics in biologically inspired AI, including neural coding, learning dynamics, and open problems in cognition, while emphasizing hands-on coding, peer collaboration, and engagement with current research. As someone who had been passively interested in NeuroAI, this course was foundational in helping me move from curiosity to genuine direction. It gave me the conceptual framework, technical skills, and intellectual community to explore the field seriously.]]></summary></entry></feed>